okay today I want to try to see if I can
roll out two different related concepts
the first concept comes from Angela
named max-neef these are called
satisfiers and the second concept is my
own and I call it reinvention so
satisfiers the idea here is to recognize
that human societies come together to
among other things
find ways to more effectively satisfy
human needs so for example we have some
number of basic human needs that we're
endeavoring to figure out how to how to
miss all we need to eat we need to sleep
and we construct different solutions to
finding ways to satisfy those needs so
I'd imagine that back in the old days we
would figure out different tools and
techniques for hunting or gathering in
preparing the things that are gathered
into edible food these are satisfiers
and these are culturally invented
culturally propagated tools in the
modern era we go out to a restaurant or
we make money and go to a grocery store
on occasion we may be grown but the idea
is that this is a basic general
framework the idea of satisfiers and the
important inside of satisfiers is to
recognize that there's two components
one is the the underlined need the thing
that actually in the sense is very solid
and enduring under most human societies
to eat is going to be a problem to be
solved and then there's the the much
more ephemeral actual satisfier the way
that we go about doing it now if you
think about the frameworks from some of
the previous episodes around like I
didn't describe attractors yet but
Fitness landscapes are reasonably close
or phase spaces or the way that
complicated systems feedback and on each
other in the danger plus model we can
also notice that satisfiers tend to get
entangled with each other so for example
as I described it earlier if you want to
go to the grocery store to buy food you
also need to figure out how to go about
getting money to be able to buy the food
so now the food satisfier is linked up
also to another satisfier associated
with in this case productivity and how
to produce goods and services in the
economy so within the satisfier concept
is only a few more things to roll out
and then i can move on to reinvention
what is that we can actually notice that
the satisfiers can be related in a bit
of a continuum that the they're good
satisfy our said as far as the
defectively go about meeting our needs
and then there are satisfiers that are
less effective at meeting our needs but
better than good satisfiers are in fact
wouldn't even call synergistic
satisfiers so this is a satisfying that
maybe meets multiple needs
simultaneously say for example going on
a picnic which might meet needs around
being in nature and conviviality with
other human beings and possibly
surfacing potential mating opportunities
or creative collaboration opportunities
in addition to eating which is very
different than say having pizza
delivered to your house and just eating
it and then the opposite side of the
spectrum are satisfiers that show up as
meeting your need but don't say for
example let's say a piece of a fast food
that doesn't actually have any
nutritional value or even worse is the
satisfier that actually makes the
problem worse so say for example a
beverage likes a Coca Cola that presents
itself as satisfying that need for
thirst for water but in fact actually
makes you thirsty ok so that's that's
the continuum of status bars to keep in
mind so so now to the topic of
reinvention if we if we notice that we
are surrounded by a social milieu of
different satisfiers that are operating
at differential levels of effectiveness
on this continuum some are synergistic
and some are in fact inhibitory
and yet we also noticed that there are
fundamental human needs and these set of
stars relate to each other very
complicated fashion we can then imagine
grasping a particular social institution
that shows up in the contemporary
environment in the environment that
we're in and endeavor to undergo a
process that I'm calling reinvention so
let's take journalism and exam as an
example so first order we to reinvent we
have to recognize that the thing that we
are dealing with is a satisfier not the
underlying need itself so journalism is
not meaningful or this is not
meaningfully understood as say for
example the media itself journalism is
not newspapers journalism it's not
television news it's not even
meaningfully the processes that work
within and give rise to those
institutional structures so journalism
is not what you learn in journalism
school journalism isn't the the
processes about how one goes about doing
good editorial these are all functional
adaptive structures inside a particular
institutional framework that to a
greater or lesser extent makes that
framework actually deliver on the need
but they aren't the thing itself so so
the thing we have to do is we have to in
some sense turn up the temperature at a
conceptual level and boil away the axes
boil away the artifacts of how we have
gone about satisfying a certain need
until we get closer and closer to the
much more solid and during core what
that need might be so in the case of
journalism we might say that the essence
of the core of journalism is a deeply
fundamental social need to effectively
source and disseminate and make sense of
our environment at a social level so to
use the the concepts of sovereignty
journalism is associated with the
exception and the intelligence portions
of sovereignty at a social level and so
there are many of us and you might
imagine it's for example in the older
times that there's a good hunting ground
over there and so journalism is the
process where the people who have
discovered that information bring it
back and share that information with the
larger tribe so that that information is
effectively disseminated throughout the
whole and now the whole can now process
that information perhaps an elder has an
interesting insight on previous times we
had similar situations and the
collective intelligence is able to make
better choices and engage in more
effective activities so it's part of a
form of group sovereignty and as such
you might say that the journalism is
actually neatly connected to science
science is also part of that same
complex it tends to maybe go more in
depth about getting more clarity on what
is the nature of things what about what
is what is true where the journalism is
more about what is but these two things
are related very closely into the
broader problem of collective sense
making and so what you can then do is
say okay great let's take the
recognition that things change and that
one particular satisfier of an
underlying need say for example the
newspapers and television news that we
developed during the 19th and 20th
century may need to be reinvented so
great well do what we just did we'll
turn the temperature up we'll try to
cause ourselves to be able to separate
from the the frameworks and
architectures that exist now boil it
down to the core essence recognizes
there's this really deep enduring social
function and then the last step is then
begin the process of endeavoring to
redesign satisfiers
in the contemporary environment say okay
great we certainly do need to have a
capacity to do social sensible you can
do collaborative sense-making but we
actually have new tools we have new
mechanisms to go about gathering
information from the edge perspectives
from a larger social whole
bringing that information in putting it
in the hands or in the minds of those
individuals or groups who are most
effectively able to make sense of it and
then allow that sense making itself to
propagate out so that people have access
to the the best perspective is the best
wisdom that's available in the larger
whole
okay so then then we just need to start
thinking about what does that look like
in the contemporary environment and what
I'd like to do just to close and I think
I'm getting to the end of the attention
span of the contemporary human is think
about this in the context of a
complicated in the complex we have a
proposition that we are reaching the the
the end of the useful life of
complicated structures and that perhaps
the the appropriate approach as we're
engaging in redesigns or engaging in
reinvention is to contemplate how we
might solve problems how we might
generate satisfiers in a in a fashion
that is more fully in alignment with
complexity and so here for example our
friend Dave Snowden has already done
deep work he's proposed an approach he
caused the human sensor network whereby
every individual human symmetrical
meaning everybody plays a role in
sensing the environment and then in
providing that sensing and since making
back into a shared social milieu and
then also in curating what is from
perception into sense and then finally
into meaning and then this can then be
handed off to a different structure
that's associated with choice making I
think that's all I want to do right now
if there's interest perhaps in the next
video I'll dig a little bit deeper into
what this human sensor network might
look like and how it quite distinctly is
different from social media and
different from a very pure information
approach that is this weird intermediary
space between the complicated and a
complex but is the kind of the
instinctual response that we have
without thinking deeply about
the nature of what are what the needs
are that we're trying to solve what the
tools are whether we have to solve them
with so